[music]
[applause]
>> Hello.
Welcome everyone at the second panel of
our conference exposing crimes is not a
crime the real world consequences of
WikiLeaks. And today we focus on the
discourse of war and military with
really great people that then you are
going to see on stage. This
topic is very important in the history
of WikiLeaks as we will see
has been important also thanks to the
activity of sources and whistleblowers
like for example Chelsea Manning that
has been very crucial for the release of
WikiLeaks in this field.
WikiLeaks of course started already
before on this subject
from 2007 with the US military equipment
in Afghanistan and Iraq but then in 2010
we have the publishing on collateral
murder and the Afghan war logs and then
Iraq war logs. And so we really have to
say that thanks to Chelsea Manning a lot
of people learn what means to face a war
crime and of course thanks to the work
of WikiLeaks that published the
documents.
And so,
I uh also
hope that the discussion of today will
bring us uh in understanding better the
presence of wars because since four year
we have been witnessing many wars uh
from Ukraine, Gaza, Lebanon um and so
also
uh Iran. And so, of course there is a
lot to say uh what is the uh still that
WikiLeaks can can teach us in
understanding
what is happening in the geopolitical
context. So, I feel also to say the that
we as the Disruption Network Lab we have
a lot of gratitude for whistleblowers
that in the field of warfare uh did a
very important act of courage uh to tell
the truth in the field of
uh criminal uh action
uh in the context of war. And so, I want
to say that uh of course uh we have to
thanks Daniel Ellsberg but also other
whistleblowers that were with us at the
Disruption Network Lab since the
beginning. Our first conference in 2015
invited as keynote uh Brandon Bryant and
many uh whistleblower of the US drone
program also been with us like Shawn
Westmorelands. We also spoke a lot about
uh Daniel Hale at the Disruption Network
Lab. Uh we invited also Reality Winner
um and so we also have to thank Heather
Linebaugh uh that we saw in the
wonderful film of Sonia Kennebeck uh for
the action that also she did in the uh
exposing war crimes. And so, today also
we will have two whistleblowers in our
panel Lisa Ling and uh John Kiriakou
together with other great speakers that
then our moderator will introduce. And
I'm happy now to introduce our
moderator, Michael Sontheimer. He's a
German journalist and also historian,
one of the founders of the daily
newspaper taz, die tageszeitung.
And so he has been reporting
on the Assange case since 2010 and
played a key role at Der Spiegel in 2012
for publishing the WikiLeaks and Edward
Snowden documents. So I'm very happy to
introduce here Michael Sontheimer and
will he will introduce the rest of the
panel. Thank you.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> Good evening. Thanks a lot.
Uh I
just introduce shortly uh
my panelistas as like as they
>> [clears throat]
>> I call them
and I have to my right, to your left, I
have Lisa Ling
um who started to work for the US
military in the early '90s as a medical
search a surgical
technique [clears throat] technician and
nurse. She transferred to the Air Force
combat communication where she
participated in operation maintenance
and security of network communication
systems.
As networks grew in size
and complexity, her unit was moved and
assimilated into the drone program.
After her military service, Lisa Ling
traveled to Afghanistan to see firsthand
the effects and the consequences of US
drone programs and targeted killings on
civilians of programs she participated
in.
And to my left, we have Jesselyn Radack.
Jesselyn Radack, if you are somehow
interested in whistleblower, you should
know her. To be honest, I've seen her in
many conferences
in Europe in the last years.
She heads the whistleblower and source
protection program at ExposeFacts.
And her work focuses on the issue
of secrecy, surveillance, torture, and
drones, where she has been at the
forefront of challenging the US
government's war on whistleblowers.
Among her clients are nationally
security and
intelligence community employees who
have been investigated, charged, or
prosecuted under the Espionage Act,
including Daniel Hale, Edward Snowden,
Thomas Drake, whom I have seen here just
a few minutes ago,
and John Kiriakou. She served on the DC
Bar Legal Ethics Committee and worked at
the Justice Department
for 7 years, first as a trial attorney
and later as a legal ethics advisor. We
don't talk about prices. Everybody of us
has won some prizes during all the
>> [laughter]
>> So, I just come
to John Goetz, who is on my left.
We should we should admit that we worked
together at Der Spiegel.
John was there in around 2010, the
WikiLeaks year. 2010 was is for
WikiLeaks year.
He was together with other colleagues.
He was
yeah, preparing the publication of the
diplomatic cables of the Afghan War Logs
and all these big scoops by WikiLeaks.
And since then, he's working for NTR,
which is a public radio in North
Germany, and for the Deutsche Zeitung.
And he made a few films. Maybe some of
you have seen one of his documentaries.
I'm happy that he is here. I'm happy
that you all are here. And last but not
least, we have John Kiriakou. Just just
on the right.
If I would find the right paper.
Oh, yeah, here we got it. John Kiriakou
is a journalist meanwhile
to say
a former CIA counter-terrorism officer,
a former senior investigator for the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee, and
a former counter-terrorism consultant
for ABC News.
He was responsible for the capture of a
high-ranking
Al-Qaeda
official in 2002.
But [snorts] John Kiriakou decided to
blow the whistle on the CIA's torture
program telling ABC News that the CIA
tortured prisoners. And
he became
indicted by the Obama administration
under the Espionage Act, served 23
months in jail.
And
yeah, as a result of these revelations,
John wrote eight books if I get it
right. And
I I only quote one, The Reluctant Spy:
My Secret Life in the CIA and the War on
Terror. Thank you all for coming, for
traveling quite a distance
to Berlin.
And let me start our talk with a very
short and simple question.
When did you come across WikiLeaks and
what did you think about the concept of
WikiLeaks when you learned about it?
Please.
>> Um
My first contact with WikiLeaks was
actually I was at Spiegel and actually
my colleague Marcel Rosenbach is here
was actually quite aware of WikiLeaks as
a phenomenon and and it was
in some ways he was like the first tech
reporter who I knew.
And we were given the job actually to go
over to London and and uh be in the
bunker at the Guardian when the initial
Afghan war logs stuff was happening.
And I mean I think there's a point in
terms of the meaning of it that that I
wanted to say and that was that
there's an aspect of WikiLeaks that I
don't think that's been talked about up
until now and it has to do
with WikiLeaks not just as a platform
for leakers but there's actually
a more
there's a political thought behind it
around this idea of courage is
courageous.
And if you think of the different models
we have of actually changing society
you know there's kind of parliamentary
democracy there's
I don't know dictatorships there's
revolution but the idea of
actually transforming the world through
leaks that actually looking at the group
of system systems operators like in the
in the world of of the internet
and actually politicizing those people
and
that there's actually a possibility and
that was the the at least the
as I understood it
and in our conversations with Julian at
the time was actually leaking as a way
to basically take the air out of power
right to pop the bubble right and not
just as like individual
leaks but actually the idea with this
courage is courageous which is why so
happy that you're here, right? Is that
it would continue. And if you actually
look at the trajectory of WikiLeaks,
right? You you have initially you have
Chelsea Manning, but actually the the
Snowden leaks are very much as a part of
that concept. Um okay, I'll shut up.
Sorry.
>> Anything else? Anybody else?
>> I I I remember exactly what I was doing
when the WikiLeaks news hit the hit the
news.
I was uh
working for John Kerry on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee staff.
And he was so appalled
that somebody would leak
these classified cables. He called the
senior staff together.
So, we had to meet in his office. And
what he wanted was a lot of bobbing
heads to say, "Yes, Senator, this is
terrible. This is appalling."
And
one of the other senior staff members
was
was a journalist, a well-known
journalist, two-time Pulitzer Prize
nominee.
And he says, "Now, wait a minute. Wait a
minute. Before we get ahead of
ourselves,
it's illegal to classify a crime. It's
illegal to classify a criminal act for
the purpose of keeping it from the
American people." Kerry didn't want to
hear that at all.
But then I jumped in and I said, "But he
he's right. You can't classify something
just because you don't want people to
know about it. If there's a video of
people being murdered in cold blood, you
can't say, "Oh,
top secret. Got to take that down." It's
a crime. There's nothing that makes it
top secret or or classified in any way.
So, we ended up arguing easily for 3
hours. And then he told us, "Just get
the hell out of his office."
That's what I was doing.
>> I I learned about WikiLeaks. I first
heard of them in 2008,
but when they were really on came just
on the map in a big way was with the
collateral murder video. And that
happened to dovetail with Obama
indicting Thomas Drake under the
Espionage Act for stuff that sounded to
me like classic whistleblowing that I
myself had engaged in, namely going
through internal channels, which didn't
work, and then going to the media.
And I remember for that I had been put
under criminal investigation for leaking
and referred to the bars I belonged to
as a lawyer and put on the no-fly list.
So, when I heard someone was indicted
under the Espionage Act, I knew that we
had really crossed the Rubicon by
unearthing this ancient law and having
it applied to someone for whistleblowing
activity. And the thing I have to say
about WikiLeaks and Julian Assange is
that when no other news outlet in the
country would touch Tom Drake and
eventually John Kiriakou and Jeffrey
Sterling and Daniel Hale and so many
other people I've been honored to
represent, WikiLeaks and Julian were
there, they were vocal, they called it
out, and this is until even recently in
Reality Winner's case, and I worked on
her advocacy, too. And again,
WikiLeaks supported whistleblowers.
That's what they did, and journalists
and people who engaged in dissent. So,
that was my how I learned of them.
>> Thank you.
>> So, so when I was introduced to
WikiLeaks, I was inside one of those
places
that WikiLeaks wanted to get into and
let loose the secrets, right?
And so, the way that I heard about
WikiLeaks, unlike a lot of, you know,
other folks that I know, was, "Don't
touch that. Don't go near that. Don't
take that gate when you leave the base
when protesters are out there. Don't do
that." And I heard it more and more,
especially when Chelsea Manning stepped
forward. You know, and they, you know, I
mean, it was the talk of inside those
secret spaces. And this is when part of
the the campaign
to um smear him in those spaces was just
ongoing. It was It was uh It was pretty
ridiculous.
And um that's what I heard. What I
didn't get to hear was things from the
other side of that secret wall. Because
they held, you know, they we were pretty
much held pretty tightly in that way.
And so, many of us were just like scared
at first to go near it.
So.
>> If I just may uh add an anecdote, uh I
heard the word WikiLeaks for the first
time when I met a
a hacker in Berlin. And we we should uh
I mean, just point out that in the
history of WikiLeaks, hackers from
Berlin played a quite important role.
So, an old friend of mine with the Chaos
Computer Club came around and said, "Uh
you're with Der Spiegel. You should meet
somebody interesting." And I met Daniel
Schmitt. He wasn't really Schmitt. He
was Domscheit-Berg.
And then he chickened out very soon
of the whole WikiLeaks project. But when
he told me what's the concept of
WikiLeaks, I thought, "Well, for a
journalist, the protection of sources is
one decide for investigative journalists
absolutely
decisive. So, the if you find a
possibility that me as a journalist, I
can get in contact with informants or
with a whistleblowers without knowing
them, that is the securest way
to
organize your relationship to
informants. So, I thought for
journalists that is a quite
revolutionary idea.
In In the end,
uh we found out that many whistleblowers
want to have contact with the editors
over the journalists. So, it's it's not
so easy, but
the but I thought, "Oh, well, for
investigative journalists, this is a
very innov- innovative, good idea."
And
uh
we mentioned already the year 2010 with
the Chelsea Manning leaks.
Have you any I mean, memories? Did they
really have an impact back then? I mean,
for us it was shocking. The The
collateral murders is still today is
absolutely shocking evidence. Uh but uh
did it have any political influence, the
the publications?
As far as I know, nobody has been put in
front of a court because of any
WikiLeaks publications.
But I don't know if this this this is
right, but
what is what do you think is
has been the impact of the 2010
publications?
>> Well, I mean, I'm curious what everyone
else has to say, but I mean, there was a
when the diplomatic cables came out,
right? There was American diplomacy was
paralyzed for several months, right? I
mean, they literally were going around
the world and
uh apologizing for things that they had
said to people
uh had said it behind the backs of, of
their partners, right? And so,
it, it basically, I mean, there's an
argument to be made that there were
other kind of American adventures that
didn't happen at that time because they
were paralyzed. So,
um, also, if you look at, at the Afghan
war logs and the Iraq war, you know, war
logs, there were also important stories
about war crimes, the task force,
whatever it was called, 170, whatever it
was, later has
turned out, actually, it's been shown to
be really as an assassination squad. Um,
those were important stories and I, and
I, actually, do think they had a big
impact.
>> Wait, do you think that the
capacities
of the US military or the, the tactics
of the US military in Afghanistan and
Iraq has been altered by the
publications of WikiLeaks?
>> I mean, I think that diplomacy was
paralyzed. I actually really
>> Diplomacy, but I'm talking about the,
not about the diplomatic cables, but
about the war, Afghani and Iraq war
documents.
>> No.
Absolutely not. Not even a little bit,
not even a tiny bit. What did happen,
um, was something that Daniel Ellsberg
used to say, um, that I was recently
talking with Jesselyn about and that is
that courage is contagious. What it did
was it showed a route where people could
come clean with actions that were
happening within their purview that were
wrong, that were illegal, that were
fraud, that were abuse because before
WikiLeaks, right, there were ways for
certain people who worked in certain
places to blow the whis, the, blow the
whistle. There were people in banks who
could actually earn money for blowing
the whistle and that was that was
something that people knew. That was
common knowledge. But when it comes to
national security, when it comes to the
things that the state is doing with our
tax dollars behind closed doors. If
you're someone working in there, it is
definitely not obvious how to blow the
whistle, how to report a crime safely.
And that, you know, that was something
that was badly needed at the time. And
that that you have to say that WikiLeaks
came through. They saw a need, they
stepped up, they met it, and um and they
started a design pattern that caught on
like wildfire. All of the sudden you're
hearing about other journalist
organization have one of those drop
boxes where you can send things. Like
that, you know, I mean to me, from my
vantage point, that was amazing. It was
something that was very much incredible,
and at the time it was very very new.
Um
and so, you know,
definitely
uh credit where credit is due. I mean,
that that whole process snowballed. And
the other thing that happened was the
idea of whistleblowing came into
conversations, everyday conversations at
the coffee table, within the secret
spaces where I worked, everywhere.
People were using the word
whistleblower. I may have heard it once
in my lifetime before WikiLeaks, but
after WikiLeaks, it became, you know,
common verbiage.
>> Other good things?
>> [applause]
>> To WikiLeaks, uh the Arab Spring was
attributed to WikiLeaks revelations.
I would say that WikiLeaks also
they pioneered the model for mass
digital document leaks
on a global level
in partnership with other news
organizations,
and they also pioneered the concept of
source protection, encryption, and
privacy. And picking up on what Lisa
said, I mean, to the extent that we now
have SecureDrop and Signal and
ProtonMail and Tails and Tor,
all of those things, WikiLeaks was at
the inception
of that and really
those technologies all have their
foundation in things that Julian Assange
said we desperately needed and tried to
make happen. And
you know, it's a tragedy the price that
he had to pay for basically establishing
the ecosystem that we have for
journalism now.
>> May I add to I think there's something
that's even more important than Chelsea
Manning's diplomatic
the release of the diplomatic cables. It
came later with the release of the Vault
7 revelations. Joshua Schulte,
God bless him, whether he
admits it or not, I think is
conversation for another time, but
but the Vault 7 revelations exposed to
the world that the CIA can take control
of your car while you're driving it by
hacking into the car's computer and send
you off of a bridge or into a tree so
that it looks like a suicide or an
accident. That that the CIA can can turn
on the microphone or the the speaker
rather of your smart TV, reverse it so
that it acts as a microphone even with
the TV appearing to be off and listen to
the conversations in your room.
What he revealed to us
really came down to matters of life or
death.
And while it was really cool to read
what
our State Department people were saying
about our diplomatic partners behind
their backs.
These really were issues of life and
death when it came to the the Vault 7
revelations.
I
you know, the first thing I did when I
when I saw the Chelsea Manning
documents was I searched for myself.
And I thought, "Dog gone that Chelsea
Manning released a cable with my social
security number in it." I was angry for
a little while. And then Ray McGovern
said, "Wait a minute. Sure, none of us
wants our social security number out
there, but there's a bigger issue here."
And it was Ray that talked me off the
ledge. When Vault 7 came out, I thought,
"My God, whoever did this did a real
public service. This was a This was a
life and death public service." And
Lisa's correct that in the beginning it
didn't affect things like covert action
or or covert operations.
It was well after uh well not well
after. It was after Chelsea Manning's
revelations, for example, that John
Brennan started to convene what what
became known as the Tuesday morning kill
list meeting.
So, WikiLeaks is out there with these
cables and John Brennan still is
scheduling meetings on Tuesday mornings
at the White House where everybody gets
together and they come up with a list of
people to kill that week. The the teams
fan out across the the globe. They kill
the people on the list and then they
meet up again next Tuesday morning to
figure out who they're going to kill
that week. That was after WikiLeaks.
So, there's still a lot more work to do.
WikiLeaks was an incredible like
once-in-a-century kind of public
service, but there's still more work to
do. And more work akin to Vault 7.
>> [clears throat]
[applause]
>> But then let me tell you that
when I remember the Vault 7, I did it
for Spiegel, I had big problems to
convince my colleagues that this is
really uh relevant [clears throat]
and it's newsworthy. I think it was more
than 20 per- portions. They were some
quite similar sometimes. And I had
really
I mean, it was not political objections,
but people said, "Oh, that's not of
public interest really. Do you think
that's for some some secret service
people who going to study all that the
because it's from the CIA." The end
and compared to the public outcry and
public impact of the 2010
it Chelsea Manning the at leaks, it
wasn't it wasn't that big. It was a sort
of secret service
a story I I would say. But but let me
ask you, do you think that if
whistleblowers are publishing
documents from the military which
goes national security,
aren't they persecuted much harder than
other whistle- whistle- whistleblowers?
That that was my impression that I mean,
you can Well, if you do something about
corruption, that's all fine. I mean,
it's not fine, but you can get problems,
but
if it really gets to the US military, I
mean, you should know what risks you're
taking.
>> Well, and that's the thing, right? So,
right now, like everybody thinks war is
all about bullets and bombs.
It's all about drones. It's all about
these things that kill people. No. What
war is really about is money.
And some of the things that was put out
by WikiLeaks showed us that war was more
than bullets and bombs. It showed us
about the diplomacy. It showed us about
the computer things that John was just
talking about. It showed us all of these
things. And then what happened was that
people's hunger to be able to have
knowledge about these things and to be
able to see these things changed in a
radical way.
More people stepped up and started
questioning what was going on behind
closed doors. Before WikiLeaks, we were
all like drones ourselves walking around
and the systems were working.
We weren't, you know, in this state of,
you know, hyper-normalcy.
Um, but after WikiLeaks came out, more
people started to question the things
that were going on around them. More
people started to question where their
tax dollars were going. More people
started to question is this idea of a
petrodollar and the idea of of wars over
oil, is this stuff real?
And those are the kind of conversations
that we need to have, right? What I I
want to see in if I were king or queen
for day for a day, right? If I were to
rule the world for 1 day, what I'd want
to see is for people to be able to let
truth see the light of day without
becoming martyrs.
I'd like to see activists hit the street
without thinking that going to jail is
their only option for publicity. I'd
like media outlets to step up and step
away from bending the knee to people in
power to actually do their freaking job.
Because we can all day long about
these wars. And we can, you know, try to
stand on street corners. We can try to
do all of these things about all the but
when push comes to shove, right now,
right now, there is an empire that's
falling. And scratching the chalkboard,
that's the elephant in the room because
the petrodollar is threatened.
And the ramifications of that are going
to be global.
And so these are the kind of things we
need people to step up and step out. We
need people who work in the tech
industry with AI, who understand the
fact that we need a whole lot more data
and that other countries have that whole
lot more data and, you you to be able so
that we can have public discourse about
what's going to happen next.
So, that's it. Thanks.
>> [applause]
>> I was just going to say since that this
is about military and whistleblowers, I
would be remiss in pointing out that so
many of the most consequential
whistleblowers in US history have come
from the military. So, as far back as
Daniel Ellsberg and and Tony Russo, Ron
Ridenhour in Vietnam, in the Iraq war,
Chelsea Manning, Larry Wilkerson, who I
think might be here, Joe Darby, again,
all military. Afghanistan war, again,
Matthew Hoh, Chelsea Manning, Danny
Davis.
Uh I mean, there's so many. Like I I I
was trying to list them all. I'm not
going to be able to And of course, in
the war on terror, drone whistleblowers
and again, also Thomas Drake and Edward
Snowden, other people. And I think part
of the reason for that is because in the
military,
unlike most
Amer-
regular Americans, if you're in the
military or you're an immigrant, you
have to take an oath to uphold and
defend the Constitution.
And I think they take that oath
seriously. And the second part of that
oath that the military take is that you
have to defend the Constitution against
all enemies, foreign and domestic.
And I think because so many people in
the military took that oath, they have
this higher calling that they have a
duty
not to the president, not to an agency
head, not to a supervisor, not to Pete
Hegseth or other or Tulsi Gabbard or any
of these other clowns, but to the
Constitution and the rule of law. And
that is like will be one of the few
saving graces going on right now. So,
thank you people in the military.
>> [applause]
>> I I just
I would
>> to do a quick shout out for Ethan McCord
who saved those children in the
collateral murder video. We often forget
about him, but the bravery that he
displayed in those moments to save those
children's lives.
Incredible.
>> I just I would not object your
observation that so many uh
whistleblowers come from the military.
But I I would say that
their cases are just much more in the
media. I mean, there are so many
whistleblowers in a little company
somewhere and never any anybody heard of
them.
And maybe they can change something and
it's
and they don't have these severe
consequences. Not every whistleblower
ends up in in jail quite soon. So,
so so I would say but the most prominent
and the most dramatic cases are
certainly in the field of military and
espionage. We're going to have an
a panel about that tomorrow.
>> Yes, but they are the least protected.
Corporate whistleblowers have have
whistleblower protection law. The people
who are not protected are people in the
US government. Specifically,
there is a carve out for national
security and intelligence
whistleblowers. And by the way, that
laundry list of people, I mean, if we
talk about Thomas Drake, John Kiriakou,
Chelsea Manning, Edward Snowden, Jeff
Sterling,
Reality Winner, Daniel Hale, military
military military. Uh
But people in the government and
military, the protections are much
weaker, especially for those doing
NatSec and Intel. And the majority of
those people I named were doing national
security and intelligence work. And to
its credit,
those were people that WikiLeaks was was
supporting and defending when no other
journalistic outlet in the US would
touch them. And I know that because a
lot of them were my clients, and we
desperately desperately needed
the a stamp of journalism rather than
journalists calling all of my clients
hero or traitor. No,
act like a journalist, don't be a
government watchdog and not a government
lapdog. And that's what I've tried to
say this whole time.
>> I add something to that, too, Jess?
Um one thing about WikiLeaks, and I
think this is a very important thing, is
WikiLeaks never got anybody in trouble.
You go to something like The Intercept,
you might as well walk up to the FBI
with your arms outstretched to to cuff
you. Right? I I We were just talking
about this earlier tonight.
After
after the fifth whistleblower was
arrested after having communication
either with The Intercept or journalists
from The Intercept, I tweeted at The
Intercept and I said, "Hey, Intercept,
serious question. You guys are an FBI
front organization, right?"
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, you must be. Or you're so
colossally stupid and lazy
and bad at your jobs that literally
every whistleblower who reaches out to
The Intercept ends up in prison.
Not with WikiLeaks.
Not at all with WikiLeaks.
We used to tell people all the time, if
you really want to leak national
security information for the purpose of
blowing the whistle on waste, fraud,
abuse, illegality, or threats to the
public health or public safety, you got
to do it through WikiLeaks because
they're the only ones who are going to
protect your identity.
>> [applause]
>> We shouldn't only praise WikiLeaks
tonight.
Though
but I I am I add one one point which is
for me as a historian and the journalist
very important is that WikiLeaks never
published a forged document or it was
never proven. And that's something I
mean if you look at the sheer number of
documents WikiLeaks has published and
not one single case and
there might be people trying to get some
forged documents that to WikiLeaks and
get them published. It never happened.
So this is quite something. And you you
want to do it. And um
But
coming back
to my question, is it the military
fields and the national security which
produces the uh
uh yeah, most dangerous and
if you look at the other side,
the whistleblowers or is it
What would you say?
>> So it's incentivization.
Bankers and bank adjacent people are
encouraged to blow the whistle to line
their pocketbooks. They actually get
rewards for doing that. And that is
something that Edward Snowden had said
that we have really twisted incentives
for doing things.
Um pretty much the entirety of the
Western world. And so what I would like
to say to any governments out there that
happen to be listening, hi y'all.
Um is simply this. If you had a problem
with WikiLeaks, fix the problem you have
with your internal whistle-blowing.
Pass legislation that supports
whistle-blowing.
Do those things and you'll never have a
problem with journalists again because
it's not the journalist stepping up and
telling the truth that is the problem.
What the problem is is that there are no
real safe ways for people to blow the
whistle on on crime, illegality, fraud,
abuse, all of that. There is no
And yet you can do it in a banking
system. And the other thing that I want
to say is look out. It's going to
change. Because corporations are no
longer going to be incentivized because
now they're working a lot of tech
corporations, a lot of, you know, uh
energy corporations, they have now
become military-adjacent
and they are now part of that huge
umbrella that's left unprotected called
the national security.
And so now we have a period of time when
we can think about what strategies we
can use to stop this rule.
Because it's going to be too late. Right
now, you know, our the US military is
purchasing things
using a venture capital model.
So, I mean, the writing is on the wall
out there.
Um and it's just it's up to people to
take the same courage that WikiLeaks
showed us so that courage can continue
to be contagious.
>> But
>> [applause]
>> What is it
If I listen to a a Jesselyn Raddack, I
might get the impression that every
Monday a new whistleblower is coming
around the corner.
It but I mean, if we look at the
publications of WikiLeaks, the last
publication of documents from the
military
the section is in 2018. I still can
remember it because I I wrote the
Spiegel story. That is now 8 years ago.
So so
we have a we have not a proper
supplier
with whistleblower. I think this this
might be a problem.
>> Yeah, well, I think I think
the country has become more and more
locked down. We have a president that uh
actively, vociferously
hates the the media and calls the media
the enemy of the people. I think also
the fact that whistleblowers have
continued to be prosecuted at a same or
even faster pace each year and they've
their sentences have gotten longer and
harsher. I mean, Daniel Hale was not
even sent At least you got a prison
camp, John. Daniel Hale was put in a
communications management unit. There
only two in the US and they were built
specifically to house terrorists. I
mean, think of what message that sent
that the whistleblower
is an information terrorist and that was
what they told the court. In reality,
Daniel Hale is a pacifist.
That was why he was
allegedly blowing the whistle on the
drone program. And again, I don't even
get me started on the intercept. Um
I won't go there. They don't deserve it,
but um
I mean, that's my point. Like
I [snorts] just feel like we are in such
a chilling climate right now.
It's hard to advise people to blow the
whistle because
they see so much proof of of I mean,
these people have been made into poster
children, including John, including Tom,
including Daniel. I mean, the long
laundry list of people who've been made
an object
of what the US government can do to you.
And I wish we had a very active
WikiLeaks
equivalent. I know the model of
WikiLeaks has been followed, certainly.
I mean, you look at the Panama Papers,
and you look at other mass exposures of
huge amounts of information.
And the tech is a two sides of a coin.
Technology makes it easier than ever to
leak, but it also makes it easier to get
caught.
>> No, I mean, I think the
>> [clears throat]
>> the idea of WikiLeaks of the systematic
cultivation of leaks as a way of
transforming society is a is is an idea
that actually is still very much alive,
right? And of course, the US government
has done everything it can it it it can
to stop that, right? I mean, it's not a
surprise, but actually the notion
of of systematically
encouraging and make and using
technology to make it safe for people to
do as an idea remains quite sound,
right?
>> And if you're thinking about blowing the
whistle, my biggest suggestion,
especially if you're from the US,
call an attorney.
>> Oh my god.
>> Call Jess.
>> Listen, in all capital letters,
this is something that I learned in my
own case from Jess.
If you're thinking of blowing the
whistle,
don't say a word until your attorney is
sitting in the chair next to you. You
don't want to be reactive. You want to
be proactive, and you want to protect
yourself.
Have your lawyer sitting next to you.
And remember, well, another thing I
learned from Jess, the morning that I
met Jess,
um it It 4 days after my arrest, and
Jess had said something very nice about
me in the Washington Post. I was having
trouble sleeping, as you might imagine.
And so, a friend of mine called me at
like 6:30 in the morning, and he said,
"Hey, there's a lady in the post. She
said this really nice thing about you,
and she's an attorney. You should call
her." And I called, 6:30 in the morning,
and she answers the phone at her desk.
And she says, "Oh my gosh, I didn't know
how to get in touch with you. I'm so
glad you called. Come into the office."
I went into the office. We met for like,
what, 2 hours? 2 and 1/2 hours. And on
the way out, I said to her, "I want to
really thank you for taking my case,
because I know that you only represent
whistleblowers, and I'm not a
whistleblower."
And you said, "You're the poster boy for
whistleblowers."
And I said, "I'm not. I'm just a normal
guy who just said something." And it was
Jess that taught me that motivation is
irrelevant.
Whistleblowing is the act of bringing to
light any evidence of waste, fraud,
abuse, illegality, or threats to the
public health or public safety.
And that has been a mantra for me
ever since.
It's not up to the politico.com
to decide if you're a whistleblower or
not. Or the Washington Post, the New
York Times. They all have their heads up
their asses anyway, excuse my language.
But this is something I've come to learn
the hard way.
You have to trust in your attorneys,
and trust in WikiLeaks, cuz WikiLeaks is
going to get the information out, and
they're going to protect your identity.
Otherwise, do exactly what your lawyer
tells you to do.
>> But come to your lawyer. Talk to a
lawyer before you blow the whistle.
Unfortunately, people come to me after
they blew the whistle, and they're being
retaliated against by the government,
and it's crushing to have the full force
of the entire executive branch come down
on you. But by then, we're already
behind the eight ball, um especially if
you're
uh and look, Trump just put another
person under the counter-intelligence
guy who said there was no reason we
didn't have any intel that Iran had a
nuclear bomb. Well, that guy is now
under a leak investigation and I bet you
dollars to donuts that it's under the
Espionage Act and his world of hurt is
only just beginning. So, again,
I I encourage people, not just me, there
are other whistleblower organizations
out there, but and many of them are pro
bono or low bono or completely free. And
you know, if you're thinking about
blowing the whistle, it's so dangerous
out there. Now, it's even more dangerous
than it was
10, 15, 20 years ago and I didn't think
I that could be possible, but it is.
Again, longer sentence, harsher
sentence, sentences that involve
torturous prison conditions,
ones that will put you in a terrorist
unit. I mean,
crazy stuff. Like talk to a lawyer
before you blow the whistle, not after.
>> But isn't that I'm what you are saying,
isn't that a deterrence for every
potential whistleblower?
I mean,
or isn't the way Julian was treated, the
long persecution of Julian? I mean, uh
>> Well, I'll qualify that. National
security and intelligence whistleblowers
in particular.
>> And I want to say the other thing about
WikiLeaks, it's like what they believed
in transparency was right across the
board. They simply believed in
transparency and what transparency is is
when you come across a whistleblower to
tell them that they need to go see a
lawyer, right? Um, because I can't tell
you how many times that journalists had
meetings with myself and my and my
friend Shawn. And we had meetings with
the journalists and all that stuff and
we had to be excruciatingly
careful about what we said and didn't
say. Um because it doesn't make any
sense for any of us to have a
whistleblower that ends up in prison. It
didn't make any sense. Um it was the
saddest thing ever was to see Assange,
Julian Assange, rotting I mean, he was
he was
the textbook example of a political
prisoner.
And so maybe, you know, the next
iteration of WikiLeaks that comes
across, there's not a person. It's, you
know, it's um it's a system.
>> Well, I have to say this also this made
me think um I've always said the war on
whistleblowers is a backdoor war on
journalists. And there should be no
doubt that war is coming in the front
door. In the US, we have journalists who
are under subpoena in a leak
investigation. We have a journalist
whose house was just searched pursuant
to a leak investigation because they
they she published a story about someone
a contractor who was blowing the whistle
on the government. Journalists are more
in the crosshairs than ever. So, it I
think it would make sense for all these
people who oh, WikiLeaks is not a
journalist. That was a worst
most ridiculous thing ever because
WikiLeaks was being prosecuted for
journalistic activity. It was being
prosecuted for protecting a source,
maintaining anonymity, using encryption,
cultivating a source. These are all
things journalists do every day and
publishing classified information.
Again, something national security and
intel journalists do
every day. So, that was such an
artificial distinction and I felt like
the mainstream media and alternative
media didn't come on board in realizing
that and saying like, oh yeah, I guess
we should defend WikiLeaks until the
very last moment. But that should have
happened 10 years earlier and it didn't.
>> [applause]
>> Nevertheless, as somebody who has been
inside a mainstream quite powerful media
Der Spiegel in these times,
it took me years, I think three to five
years, that I could write a
journalist or publisher. They wanted me
to write an activist called Julian
Assange an activist. And that that also
was the case with
Reporters sans frontières.
They first in the beginning they said
journalism like activities they called
what WikiLeaks was doing. So it was a
struggle also from people inside the
media
to to to accept that whistleblowers have
to be
protected, that they play important role
in in the critical journalism.
That was quite hard. It was and as you
might know, I'm
I'm a journalist since 50 years now.
Um
journalists are not very don't have that
much courage most of them. So
>> [laughter]
>> the it is the it is
you have to to deal with people who if
there are some
is a political constellation or if the
owner of a newspaper is having this
point of view, they see where they what
they should do. So it's
>> I realize I realize journal some
journalists, some of them
don't have the courage, but you sure as
should not burn your source. Those
journalists and
I'm not going to say their name because
again their lawyers will descend upon me
because that has happened in in past.
But a particular outlet and particular
journalists particular outlet has been
responsible for sending multiple
whistleblowers to prison, and that is
shameful. Shameful. And uh
>> Well, what's what's crazy about I just
remember this thing that went on in
Germany for many years, and it was this
whole thing, you know,
>> [clears throat]
>> uh you know, is what you know, is
WikiLeaks or is Assange an activist or
is he a journalist? And it was just like
this kind of And you never ask the
question is Murdoch an activist or a
journalist, right? Like there's like
never ever or Springer, right? There's
never a question is Springer an active,
you know, Springer as a publishing house
activist. And that question was always
reserved for WikiLeaks. And you had
these like kind of conversations in the
editorial rooms I've been in in my life
that constantly went back and forth, you
know, can you actually call him a
journalist? And all I remember is
actually like with Marcel, we were in
this room with the other journalists,
Julian is sitting there. We're all
looking through the data, and we're
saying, "Oh, look what I found. Look
what I found." We were working together
as journalists to analyze the Afghan war
logs. That was an act of journalism.
>> But, I think it's happened to you as
well. I was called an activist because I
was supporting
WikiLeaks and Julian Assange
and the campaign. And but then I I I
used to answer, "If I am a journalist,
and I don't defend freedom of press, I
just lost it." So, and that's what we
were doing basically as journalists. We
were defending Julian because we we
thought it is the right
to publish certain things the government
doesn't like.
>> What were you accused of? What
What kind of criticism did you get?
>> They sent when I I did interviews with
Julian in the embassy in London, they
sent some kind of policeman from from
the editorial staff that that that I
don't fraternize too much or I don't
know. It was ridiculous anyway. But but
somehow Julian and the whole issue
maybe because of the Americans were were
behind it.
In Germany people said oh very difficult
with Julian Assange and
so it it wasn't not a very clear
understanding that defending freedom of
press means defending WikiLeaks.
Well
>> The
another thing I just wanted to mention
up here this poor man here is the only
one from Europe. We're all from you know
pretty much um
I mean
this is like we a lot of times I hear it
said that you know the US is doing this
the US is doing that. But what what Jess
was just talking about journalists being
arrested it's happened in Australia.
It's happened in the UK. So I mean while
we can look at the US right now and
we're doing really poorly we are not
making friends. We suck right now let's
be real okay. But what happens is it
ripples throughout the world. And so
like all of the stuff that we're saying
here it applies to the western world.
Um maybe not today maybe not tomorrow
but it it it does and I'm sorry that a
lot of it does come out of the US. I'm
sorry. But um but we all need to start
paying attention to these things. We all
need to support you know journalism. We
all need to support um whistleblowers.
We all need to support
operations like WikiLeaks and we all
need to support I mean the other thing
that's not been mentioned is the gross
over classification of bazillions of
documents and things that are just
classified to all classification.
It's utterly ridiculous. It's like when
the US got their first computers they
thought that three would be enough for
the country.
And then they thought, "No, that's not
enough." And then they started printing
documents because they could print
documents, and there were like
bazillions of documents in the military,
and they were so overloaded with
documents that they ended up having to
buy computers so that they could get rid
of all those documents.
Well, imagine that whole problem like
feedback loop happening in the spaces
that the rest of the world isn't allowed
to see.
Cuz it's there.
>> Yeah, over-classification continues to
be a problem. The US has lost track of
how much information it has classified
because of the over-classification
problem, and it continue I mean,
it's only going to continue to get
worse. And the process to actually I
mean, if the government can technically
declassify a document,
it rarely decides that it needs to do
that. It's people fighting through the
Freedom of Information Act and other
tools to And so,
thank you to all the journalists out
there who've been fighting to get stuff
declassified, but there's so much stuff
that's needlessly classified, and you're
not allowed to classify. You can
classify to hide sources and methods or
conceal undercover identities, but you
can't do it, as Lisa said, because the
leaks might embarrass you. And a lot of
the stuff that's being classified is
stuff that Luckily, it gets out there
through leaks. Thanks to leaks. And one
of the biggest leakers right now, one of
my favorite leakers right now, is Pete
Hoekstra. That dude has leaked more
stuff
than
than many whistleblowers. And active war
plans. I I to the extent Julian was
accused of, you know, leaking stuff
about war plans, holy cow. He leaks
stuff about an air war actually
Yeah, on signal with the journalist
in the loop. So, there you go. I mean,
and and that wasn't an isolated
incident. I mean, Hick Seth has and and
Tulsi Gabbard
both have been accused
of leak leaky problems. So,
>> And neither Hick Seth nor the journalist
got locked in an embassy. Neither Hick
Seth nor the journalist got like
completely prosecuted. Prosecuted.
Nothing like that happened.
So,
>> Yeah, Hick Seth is well, he's under
investigation supposedly by the
Inspector General, but that will take
years and go nowhere and especially
because
>> them.
>> Oh, yeah, they did fire that one.
True, they fired most of the Inspectors
General, but
that's why the fourth estate and the
press is more important than ever right
now because the press and a few good
judges are the only bullwark right now
of democracy.
>> But but let's be more specific about
that, too. It's mostly the independent
press.
You know, there's a wonderful
journalist, Jason Leopold, at Bloomberg,
investigative journalist.
George W. Bush's Pentagon spokesman
called him a FOIA terrorist
because he has filed more Freedom of
Information Act requests than any other
person on the planet Earth.
And he told me once that he was bored
one year over Christmas break, and so he
dashed off a Freedom of Information Act
request to the CIA for every
communication between the CIA and an
American journalist for the previous
year.
Period.
>> [laughter]
>> And what he does, he still does it now
that he's with Bloomberg, he has a
lawyer friend
um who sues the CIA. The The law is
clear. The CIA has 60 days to respond.
They never You'll be lucky if they
respond in 60 years.
So, he sues on day 61, and he always
wins because the law is clear, and the
CIA always has to pay his legal fees
because he won.
So, he does this over Christmas, and he
gets thousands of pages of documents,
but they include a couple of golden
nuggets.
One of them
showed that Ken Dilanian, who is the
chief national security correspondent
for NBC News and what was called MSNBC,
was writing his articles
and sending them to the CIA for
clearance before sending them to his own
editors.
Is this okay with you guys if I say
this? Cuz if it's not okay, I'll just
take it out. So, just let me know.
Another thing that he found was there
was a young, hungry, independent
journalist who actually found a scoop
and wrote to the CIA and said, "I'm
going to print this tomorrow. Do you
have any comment?" And they responded,
and they said, "So help us God, if you
print this tomorrow, you will never be
invited to the CIA Christmas party ever
again."
>> [laughter]
>> That's what they said. And we will never
give you any background briefings.
And he killed his own story.
But we would never know any of this if
it wasn't for good, independent
journalists, fearless journalists, like
Jason Leopold,
and journalists that rely on WikiLeaks
for some of those leads that they can
then dig into cuz the mainstream media
is not going to do it. It's not going to
be in the New York Times, in the
Washington Post, and the Wall Street
Journal, or CNN, or Fox, or anywhere
else. It's just not going to appear.
>> Yeah, but I mean, you also have to
remember that the initial WikiLeaks, you
know, material from 2010 did run in the
New York Times, did run in the Guardian,
and did run in Spiegel, right? I mean,
that was the I mean um
>> Le Monde and El País as well.
Le Monde and El País as well later.
>> I mean, it you know, that
it did happen.
>> I don't know we are not we are not all
journalists here, but
if you talk about this kind of tactical
relationships to what secret service I
can remember that Edward Snowden in the
midst of a really difficult production
asked us to confront the GCHQ
that with the facts in our story and we
we thought it couldn't be. We always
could could do it without confrontation,
but he insisted
on that,
but
it it went nowhere because these secret
services they want to ask
what's the
color of the hair of your colleague
who's working with or what's the size of
her shoes and stuff. They they ask you a
lot they want to know everything and
they won't tell you nothing. They just
give you this statement which you can
put on your wall and take every time you
call the secret service. So, it is it
can be tactical.
It can make sense to talk with secret
service people. I just had a good laugh
with them sometimes and
so, but but this is journalist talk. The
I would I would get it back into the
political realm and and the
and the
let's about WikiLeaks.
When we look in the future and we all
wish I think that WikiLeaks would
be reborn. I mean, it doesn't really
exist as as if you look at the website.
There there hasn't been things
published.
So, we all hope that it will be reborn.
I'm asking myself after Daniel Ellsberg
said, "I've been waiting for Chelsea
Manning for Was it 40 or 50 years?"
We don't have that many whistleblowers.
I mean, don't you know what happened to
a whistleblower? Just yourself. I mean,
it is a risky job. And I mean, there are
organizations luckily and and attorneys
and lawyers who support whistleblowers.
But I don't know how we can create more
whistleblowers. I mean, politically it
would make a lot of sense, but how to do
it?
>> I think you need to have better
whistleblower protection and Chip
Gibbons, who was on a panel earlier, has
been working on
an act to reform the Espionage Act in a
way that would protect whistleblowers,
protect journalists, create a public
interest defense, so you could actually
say in court at trial that I did this. I
blew the whistle because what I saw was
wrong and people were dying because of
it. Right now, you can't make that
argument until sentencing after you've
already been found guilty.
>> But if you murder somebody, but if you
kill somebody in cold blood standing
outside the building, you can make that
>> Sure.
>> argument at trial and twice on Sundays.
>> And to make it even more difficult, if
you plead guilty to a lesser charge, you
are forbidden by law from ever launching
an appeal
or filing a Freedom of Information Act
request on your own case.
Can't do it.
>> Yeah, and then you come out and you have
a criminal record and it complicates
your life for the rest of your life as
John knows, as Daniel knows.
Um
Yeah, it's a terrible situation. I mean,
I
>> I mean, whistleblower is an American
word and uh
But it looks like what sounds like what
you are saying telling tonight that if
the situation of whistleblowers in the
United States is much worse than
than many other countries, is that true?
>> Don't forget Katherine Gun. Look what
happened to her in the UK. And she
contemporaneously
said, "Hey, this is what's happening
with the war in Iraq." Before the war
started.
And it went nowhere, but her life is
forever changed.
>> I think it's gotten worse. The situation
for whistleblowers, as bad as it was, um
when Obama
yeah, under Obama,
the the transparency president, um
by
you know, indicting Tom Drake,
I mean, it just set off what I I thought
it was a one-off, but it unfortunately
has become completely normalized at this
point. Like I said, I mean, the news
yesterday that another guy is being
investigated by the FBI for a leak,
because he said something that was
dissent, not because he Well, I think
they're saying he revealed classified
information, but they always say that.
And a number of times that turns out not
to be true.
Um
this is a it is normalized to use the
Espionage Act. And so, unless we do
something
like Chip is working on and repeal the
Espionage Act, I don't see an end to
this. I mean, the government has found a
loaded gun, a very useful tool that it
can use. And the defendant is not
allowed to mount a defense. And the
proceeding will take place largely in
secret because of classification. Even
if stuff was unclassified, in Thomas
Drake's case, all the information at
issue turned out to be completely
unclassified.
And yet
all of these proceedings were taking
place in a classified information
procedure act hearings in a skiff in
a Kafkaesque secret locked down
situation. Same with Daniel Hale, my own
client. Even in an open court session,
I, his lawyer, one of his lawyers, was
shut out even though they were not
discussing classified.
Uh
is that constitutionally
challengeable?
Maybe, but by then the horse has left
the barn and the client's already in
prison. You know, I so
we we really need to rein in computer
fraud abuse act, the Espionage Act, and
these laws that are being used largely
against whistleblowers and journalists
and not against people who are actually
committing what we think of as saboteur
or spy conduct.
>> So, before we
Yeah, take questions of the audience,
maybe a last question from me and
for all of you.
That if you can if you could look into
the future, what would you wish
WikiLeaks would be in let's say
[clears throat] 10 years time?
>> I would love to see it active again, but
I also, given what WikiLeaks went
through, which was literally
uh this campaign by one of the the most
powerful countries in the world,
including attempts and designs to
assassinate
Julian Assange,
I get why they're not reconstituting. I
think we're in a very chilling
environment and I I don't know if I
as much as I would like to see WikiLeaks
or a similar type organization
exist, I don't think it would. I think
it would the government would quickly
label it a terrorist, label its
editor-in-chief or publisher
a terrorist, get them blacklisted,
financial blockades, all the stuff that
happened to WikiLeaks, but now on
steroids because I don't recognize the
country I was born in,
uh the US.
>> Yeah, I I have to agree.
The the only way that
not just the American people, but any
people are going to know about
government malfeasance is through
WikiLeaks. We need a robust, healthy,
and well-funded WikiLeaks. It's the only
way to to keep the honest people honest.
>> I just don't know if that can happen
given this climate. I mean, it would
have to be run out of another country
for sure.
And and anyone from the US who's
cooperating with it, as we have seen,
including people who were not part of
WikiLeaks. Um
Again, it's an incredibly dangerous
environment in which reporters,
and not just sources now, but reporters
and even people who were just war
protesters have been put in jail at a an
astonishing number.
>> That's Yeah, that's true in the US. What
I would like to see, if again, if I were
queen for a day, is that
journalism such as what WikiLeaks did
be legal.
Period.
I would like to call what WikiLeaks did
journalism.
And be done with all of this BS where
power just crushes people's voice.
Period. Cuz I I mean, I don't know about
anyone else, but I am incredibly
sick of having to do what Daniel Hale
said in the national bird. He said I've
always walking around and I got to watch
my words. I always got to watch my
words.
And it's like I know all of us who came
here from the US are thinking what are
we going to do at the airport?
How are we going to get in? How much are
we going to be searched? I am sick of
that So like, you know,
>> My mantra is
you cannot stop me from reentering my
own country.
And that's the end of the conversation.
Maybe you sit there for 45 minutes. One
time I sat there for 4 hours, but every
single time they would say, "Let me see
your phone. Let me see your laptop." I
would say, "Not without a warrant and
you can't stop me from reentering my own
country." And then finally they say,
"Just get the hell out of here."
>> [laughter]
>> Well, that problem was just solved.
>> I mean, just as a journalist, I would
love to get leaks and
material and documents and publish them.
Yeah.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Thank you.
>> Now, please any questions to
all of us
anybody here on stage?
I can't see from here.
>> Yes, there's a lady in the middle here.
>> There's a lady on the right here.
>> Oh, okay then. Okay.
>> Thanks.
It's been fascinating to see
to see the world
in real life rather than on the little
screen.
I have a question.
Some things have
changed since
since 2010.
In
2010,
we needed
collateral murder
or
the release of
the Abu Ghraib cable which helped
remove immunity from
um
from American soldiers in Iraq.
To send
>> tortured Muslim men tortured at
Guantanamo.
WikiLeaks which were courage,
ingenuity,
purpose, public-spiritedness.
Where are you seeing one or more of
those today?
>> That's easy.
Wherever the US is oppressing a country.
That's I mean, Palestine, those
journalists facing life and death
getting the truth out there. The people
who are filming inside of, you know, the
camps that are in the US holding people
who were illegally in the country,
which, you know,
um
everyday citizens who get online and
they're all over in the streets blowing
whistles and following ICE.
That's where we see it. What we don't
see
is more people standing up for them
because
we have to fight back in numbers. If we
don't have those numbers, we lose before
we ever start. And so, you know, for
people who free Palestine, man. Free
Palestine, right? And what about the
genocide that's going on in Africa?
Like,
um
>> [applause]
>> what about, you know, I mean, there are
so many countries that are being
oppressed and there are so many people
who are trying to stand up with their
very lives. Like um my heart goes out to
them cuz they don't have the privilege
that I have as a white woman in this
world.
>> [applause]
>> Yeah, who was next?
Uh maybe in the middle. Yep.
Yeah, thank you very much for this talk.
Um
it was really inspiring, but
unfortunately tomorrow we will wake up
and we will have our shitty German
journal again. So, I'm talking about
all the journal that we know. I mean, do
not have to cite them one by one, but
even looking outside of the German
countries, we will have Italian journals
or
in France or in Spain. And to me, to
reconnect to what she was saying,
uh it's sad to say, but honestly, um
it's difficult to see the impact of
WikiLeaks
now in our journal. And I'm talking
about the mainstream journal. So, you
were saying before that we need more
whistleblower.
And some of you say that we need more
uh journalists with courage. Um
I think that the main problem is
publisher,
especially talking in this country.
And maybe some of the journalists in in
the panel can tell us something more
about it. But my question is, how do you
think this problem can be solved? So, um
we have a platform, we have
whistleblower, we have journalists.
Actually, there are journalists with
some courage, but those journalists,
they do not get a job.
It's really difficult for a for good
journalists to to find job.
And and so, this is why uh we have
publisher that they have really crappy
journalists, especially when it is about
I mean,
international politics.
I'm at Germany right now, but this this
discussion can be extended outside of
the country. So, my question is, how can
be the publisher landscape be changed in
your opinion? Thanks.
>> Uh, John, would you I mean, you are a
journalist. I'm also a journalist. Would
you like
to say something about the publisher?
Because my impression is different. I
think at the moment, if you have got
some documents about um,
US war crimes,
they would be published here easily.
Because I mean, the relationship between
Germany and the
US government, the current US
government, so strained that no German
publisher would It's something different
with Gaza. Gaza is a complete other
story which has to do with the German
past. But, American documents, there is
no publisher who is
who's not giving a good journalist a job
or who who would say, "We don't We don't
work with these documents." I I don't
see that like that. But, John,
>> No, no, no. I That's I I agree. I mean,
I think I think right now
[clears throat] the atmosphere is very
much, I mean,
I think one of the issues that you see
in German journal- journalism is that
counter narrative, which is the kind of
the traditional,
you know,
field of investigative journalism, that
kind of
>> [clears throat]
>> takes current affairs and actually looks
that at at the narrative from a
different point of view.
In Germany,
a lot of editorial staffs are really
worried that that's the realm of the
AfD, right? And if you come with the
counter narrative proposal, right? They
don't distinguish between,
I don't know if you want to say
left-wing or kind of, you know, critical
counter narrative and AfD counter
narrative. And you see these editorial
people like very confused and worried
about oh my god, where you know, is this
going to help Russia? Is this going to
help the AFD? Is this going to be and so
they stay very centrist because they're
worried about kind of the broader
implications of it. That's how I That's
what I experienced. Put it that way.
>> [applause]
>> There was someone in the first panel
asking or making this comment about the
fact that the
the internet is is somewhat of a
cesspool now and that digital
communications are are really
problematic that we're not necessarily
going to be able to operate with another
kind of WikiLeaks. I hope that there are
ways, but
in case that we need to look at other
things, I think it's important maybe to
think about for this whole conference
maybe not to be so media and
data-centric
and to think about ways of resistance in
other forms
because we have enough information to
know we're being ruled by corrupt
bastards and people who are doing war
crimes and things like that. Uh recently
Andrew Feinstein was here to speak on a
panel and he was speaking about the
multiple factors that brought down
apartheid in South Africa. And so the
other really important key things are,
you know, popular uprising, divestment
from
from uh you know, in academics with with
military industrial complex things
and
uh other factors. Uh but this
multiplicity of things that that happen
in a confluence are the things that can
topple the power, but if we just keep
looking for more information, we're just
going to drown in it. So, I'm wondering
you know, is was the internet anyway in
some sense, you know, always military
industrial complex and we were not
really looking in the right direction to
liberate ourselves through the
technological tools of the master.
What do you think about that angle?
>> So, I have something very critical to
say.
Get off Google. Cuz like all the people
that are doing all these other things
that are brilliant,
they are communicating with Gmail. So,
like I mean, to come back to the wish
for WikiLeaks and the folks around
WikiLeaks, please,
create another Google so that activists
can communicate. There's been several
people who have tried to put that
forward and tried to do that, and
they've all failed. There's been a lot
of grift in that arena. Um but we need
something else because the problems are
now global. So, we're going to need to
be communicating with the technology,
and all technology is dual use. And has
it always been a tool? Well, yeah. The
US military pretty much invented it.
The CIA got on board, you know, like So,
has it always been military? Yeah. Yeah.
But I mean, so have Jeeps.
And so have many things that we use.
So, um
we can use this effectively. We can use
technology effectively.
But um we need to find alternatives like
uh
Meredith Whittaker's trying to come up
with a new business model for Signal.
And what she's doing is working.
ProtonMail is trying to have a new
business model, but as some of you may
or may not know, because of um
intergovernmental agreements, ProtonMail
was compromised by an intergovernmental
agreement where they were able to get
the information of who was communicating
with who.
So, I mean, we need to find other
alternatives to be able to communicate
to let these things
flourish.
>> But I agree, you need multiple tools in
your toolkit and they should go beyond
just communication. We need boots on the
ground in the street, marching protests,
go go to Parliament, go to your
legislatures,
and lobby for things like Chip has been
championing championing trying to end
the Espionage Act.
Take a multi-pronged approach, play to
your strength, whatever your strength
is. If you're a lawyer, if you're a
journalist, whatever your strength is,
use that to fight this. But also,
people in the streets matter, organized
protests matter. That was an essential,
and Stella talked about this, the
protests, the organic protests that
sprung up all over, not only the US, but
the world in support of Assange, and
everyone did it kind of differently, but
you still had all of these different
arenas of protest, and it really was
horseshoe politics, because you had like
very liberal people, very conservative
people, libertarians. I mean, you just
had like people of all political stripes
realizing
that what was affecting and what was
coming down on WikiLeaks could easily
rain down on them, and it took that kind
of continued, persistent, vocal
solidarity, and it was a grind over
many, many, many years. I mean, again,
the persecution of Julian was not just
Belmarsh, and it started so much longer
before, and I think a lot of
don't quite realize how much of Julian's
life was spent in some kind of
confinement situation before Belmarsh
and before the embassy. I I
how much of his own life had been
sacrificed for transparency. So, we need
to carry that forward.
>> [applause]
>> I mean, and let's also not forget that
there was a lot of people who went to
jail who who were not named Julian
Assange having to do with WikiLeaks,
right? You know, Ola Bini, right? You
know, you know, Shalta as you mentioned.
I think Jeremy Hammond is and and also
the people who basically refused to give
states evidence against WikiLeaks who
basically also got criminalized and had
criminal prosecution, you know, you
know, prosecutions or
threatening letters or, you know,
whatever and basically were forced to
live outside of the United States. So, I
mean, it it Sure, the focus of course
was on Assange and
and of course it was right to to get him
out, but I'm saying it's amazing
actually how many people were actually
hit with that state repression.
>> [applause]
>> Yes, last question or questions
uh back there.
All the way back.
>> Yes, thank you very much. I would like
to follow up on the question of what is
there left to whistle-blow if there is a
genocide that is live-streamed and my
question is there Is there anything left
to scandalize?
Um I hate to be fatalistic, but I I this
you know, it crossed my mind and I want
I want to know if you So, we can
scandalize if there is a desire for
truth, right? If there is something that
we can say that is a scandal. So, we see
now with the war on Iran and on Lebanon,
we don't know we said one day it is this
reason, the other day it is that reason.
Would there be in the current war any
tipping point case, any question that we
could scandalize to actually say, yes,
this would be a problem for them to
continue the war? Because they're quite
vocal that they're doing these wars just
for this. Uh so, they're breaking the
law. Yes, we're breaking the law. Is
there
So, they're they're doing a actually
criminal things and they're admitting it
themselves. So, my question is really,
yes, is there
is there anything we can scandalize when
Trump says, the only law is my moral
judgment?
>> Jeffrey Epstein.
Yeah, okay.
>> [laughter]
>> No, I mean
to the extent this war is meant to
distract and unfortunately seems to have
successfully distracted
Americans from focusing on the Epstein
scandal, which potentially, if we
actually had access to the documents and
if we ever needed WikiLeaks or an
organization like WikiLeaks, it would be
for the Epstein files. I mean, who
wouldn't want to see that?
All of it. Not the redacted version, not
the sanitized version, not the version
that's protecting, in Trump's words,
all my friends.
That would be an amazing thing to leak.
Remember when WikiLeaks created the list
of documents that it wanted to be
leaked?
That was important. I could come up with
a list of those documents, but again,
I don't see the public clamoring or
making the connection that that is
precisely the kind of mass trove of data
that WikiLeaks was able to get out there
in in pristine form, in the form in
which it was written without government
redactions and and blank pages.
>> I I just want to respond directly to
you. I I actually think
um
what definitely is you know would be a
scan you know would be journalistically
really relevant right now would be
secret treaties between Gulf states and
the United States and Israel. I think
uh internal documents from Egypt right
now about the agreements about the
border
uh with Gaza. I agreements between
Israel and Egypt would be highly
interesting right now. I mean I think um
the uh material about
um the
you know anti-missile defense systems
and how they've been moved around
um
uh I think also like you know we're in
Germany right now. What what did Germany
know about the war before? What is
Germany doing actually right now because
we have a you know a history of
situations where Germany has once you
know has said publicly for example with
the Iraq war we're not going to
participate and in the end they ended up
doing targeting for the United States
military in Baghdad, right? I mean even
though the public you know the public
population wasn't aware of that. Um so I
think there's a lot of stuff right now
that would be really interesting to hear
about. Also
any note taking between conversations of
Netanyahu and Trump. I mean that stuff's
out there. It would be great to get and
I actually think it would uh
scandalize people.
>> There are also people online with
questions.
>> Yeah there there was one one here
at first row and then
this one and then we go to the
online questions.
>> intelligence agencies themselves have
largely been shifting their center of
gravity towards open source
intelligence. When WikiLeaks released
the Kissinger cables, there was
you know, a lot of confusion from the
press of oh, do you just do open
information now or you done with leaks?
You know, the the point was made no, the
point is the analysis like what you
learn, not you know, the methodology.
And so, I think obviously
techniques for analyzing broader sources
of information. There was reference to
live stream genocide. You can find this
all on Instagram. Like what do you view
as the role of evolving into the world
of, you know, broader forms of
intelligence and let's say open source
intelligence of of WikiLeaks is a center
of gravity now.
>> Now, that's basically the question to
WikiLeaks which is sitting in the first
row,
not very far from you.
And and just let let me make one point.
I think we
just touched certain questions. What's
going to be with WikiLeaks? Will there
be a new organization and so on? And I
hope very much that we going to discuss
these questions
tomorrow
and the next days because I think I've
never met such a intense
I mean,
such a big number of former WikiLeaks,
still WikiLeaks, friends of WikiLeaks,
supporting WikiLeaks, lawyers and so on.
So, we we going to talk about that in
the next days.
The uh
To to your question, to be to be honest,
you know, that's
>> your question. I think that all of us
need to learn a little bit of open
source intelligence so that we can dig
through the like
the plethora of garbage that's now
online and find, you know, the actual
truth of things.
Um and the other thing is
um it would be great if there was a
repository like WikiLeaks for
open-source information, for any
information because, you know, it's just
like with whistleblowing, the messenger
doesn't matter, it's the message.
And so in this case, the method doesn't
matter, it's still the message that's
important and how we get it out there to
the public. And how we, you know, make
it in a way that the that the general
public eat in bite-size chunks so the
general public can understand it.
I don't know, did that work?
>> So there was one last question online, I
think. Over there and then we go.
>> Hi, just building up on what was said
till now. Uh
we had the WikiLeaks coming out, all the
cables, and
but the effect the net effect that is
that then Trump got elected.
I think
the fact that it didn't really
change the mind of people that when we
are
whistleblowing, coming out with with
with scoops, we see that that doesn't
affect the public opinion. I mean, we
have a problem on this. Now, to the
point that the criminals are making
selfies while they committed a genocide.
And that makes our job, I'm a I'm a
reporter myself, very
difficult. You know, what can I say
more? When they kill
how many are there now? I don't know.
50,000? Only it doesn't matter anymore,
the number of kids of children killed in
Gaza. When they carpet bomb Tehran
without any any reason, how can we do
more than this? If people doesn't rise
out of these elements that are very
clear to everybody,
what can really make them rise up? This
is my my
my fear that we are lobotomized, that
the people doesn't really have the the
capacity of react to such they flooded
us as Bannon like to say, you know, they
flooded us with so much that we
don't even realize what is going on.
This is why we becomes, I'm sorry,
irrelevant.
Sometimes to
>> What's your question?
>> So, the question is
is maybe is the political is a political
problem. So, it's not just a
journalistic problem, but there is a
political you say you were saying before
that there is not
we we are trying not to be political,
but maybe here is a big political
problem that is cannot be resolved by
only by journalism.
>> I mean
Nothing can be
solved only by journalists. I'm I'm very
sure as a journalist.
But
but I have the impression that war
creates a lot of horrible things, but it
also creates whistleblowers. If I look
at the work of the +972,
which is Israeli
internet
platform, they had quite a few really
interesting the whistleblowers from from
the IDF.
So, so I think
we going to see and specially about this
revolution of introducing AI in into war
modern warfare. The I mean
Some [clears throat] stuff was already
coming out and I I think we going to
hear and and read and see from
this kind of information that quite
frequently in the in the future. So, in
that way I'm optimistic. What that
causes
or what political impact that has on
societies
on the political actions or not non
action is another question.
>> I'm working with the AI whistleblower
initiative on whistleblower protections
for AI. And if you haven't noticed,
there have been a huge number of
whistleblowers in AI, which is sort of
the new frontier to me it's what
cybersecurity was
10 years ago, 20 years ago and now AI.
But
the people who've been blowing the
whistle on AI are a lot of people at the
top. And they've been doing so by
resigning and resigning loudly and
talking about
problems with the technology. So that
gives me a
just to end this with like a little tiny
glimmer of hope.
>> All right. Now
>> [clears throat]
>> questions from the
in famous in the internet.
Who has them?
>> Yes.
How can military whistleblowing continue
to feel impactful in a climate of
engineered distrust, learned
helplessness, and the normalization of
atrocities?
Case in point, the genocide in Gaza.
And how do we convince potential
whistleblowers and the public that
people are actually held accountable as
a result of leaks?
>> [laughter]
>> I mean
I don't know that there's an answer to
that question
anywhere, but I do know that something
that Edward Snowden said rings true to
me and it's that we need to to change
the incentivizations that we have. And
like one of the things that we're doing
with this political
quagmire that we're in is that we're not
able to work together and sometimes even
from the polar left and the polar right,
I mean polar opposite people, it's
something that was said at the first
panel about it being a really long
process and finding ways that we can
work together on a single goal. And I
think a lot of
you know, I mean and and and
it's really hard because you know, it's
like people are not eat so I don't know
if it's self-censoring or censored that
we're not even, you know,
shall I say allowed to say that that was
a genocide?
It was a flipping damn genocide.
And it's still going on. And so I think
one of the other things that we need to
do is just shout that stuff from the
rooftops. I don't know how to break, you
know, this this apathy, this
hopelessness, this I mean
it's like
this is what trauma does. And right now
we have entire nations in trauma.
>> [applause]
>> Thanks.
Are there any more questions? I will say
it's last question. It's not
up there. Oh, sorry.
It's the lights are
Could Could somebody get a mic up there?
We completely neglected the upper floor.
>> Okay, thank you for your
remarkable work as whistleblowers, first
of all.
I wanted just to bring the attention to
like what we just talked like
what is the point of a whistleblower if
then we don't do anything with it?
Like in the sense
for example like setting the tone of
like it seems like
the tone that was set in this
conversation was very reformist in the
sense of like how can we for example lay
hope in the US government
to reform and act like a the Espionage
Act and then be like, okay, the US
government will protect now
whistleblowers. Like or for example now
when like
the the question previous to the last
question it asked like when we talk
about activism, when we talk about like
how like
we should also focus on like what is
actually like the
counter like the parallel channel to the
institutional channel because it cannot
just be journalism for the sake of
journalism and it cannot just be
um
it cannot just um we cannot just hope it
like the perpetrator becomes the
protector.
So, how do you envision this? Do you
think that like WikiLeaks have like more
of the purpose of like just blowing the
whistle or in order to make it congruous
with the
fight and the struggle in the world
actually, you should have like a
political meaning in the sense of
connecting with this activism.
Thank you.
>> I mean, there was another trajectory for
WikiLeaks after 2010
and that was that it would become an NGO
that would get American government
financing and basically
became become a lame operation, right? I
mean, that was really that was one
possibility that WikiLeaks could have
gone in
and you know, um and I think it's a real
credit to Assange actually himself that
that WikiLeaks remains an organization
that openly violated
um
you know, I mean, didn't ask for
permission to do anything and didn't
wait for a law to get changed. It was
actually
uh as in its concept outside of that and
was not begging for permission to do
things and I think that's why it stayed
such a strong organization and didn't
become yet another NGO.
>> [applause]
>> Well,
>> It was all It was a journalistic
organization, too. I mean,
I still think that that there are
journalists that need to step up and and
freaking tell the truth and use the word
fascism. Use the word Words matter. Like
use the word genocide. Use the words,
you know, slaughter. Use the words
imperialism. Use I mean,
words matter and as long as we keep like
relegating war to business-like terms
and relegating like some of the worst
things that humankind does into like
organizational transactional terms, then
we're just going to remain in this kind
of lethargy.
>> [applause]
>> All right.
Thank you, Lisa. Thank you, John.
Thank you, Jesselyn. Thank you, John.
I think you were quite you were great
a panel here
because I mean, it's it's a sometimes
depressing and very serious
topic we were talking about, but
sometimes I could even have a good laugh
about
certain anecdotes and about certain
remarks.
I hope you will come back tomorrow
because the I mean, all these
questions about WikiLeaks should be
discussed by people who are closer to
WikiLeaks or who are WikiLeaks and I'm
looking forward
to listen to these
these discussions tomorrow. Have a good
evening.
Have a
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> And you're actually we can actually
continue [music]
talking if you want. We We all go eat
and drink at the restaurant of Hau,
which is at Hallesches Ufer 34, at the
Parallelstraße, the parallel street, so
you can we can still continue there.
Thank you. You're invited.
>> [music]
[music]